《福尔摩斯历险记》
你答应了的
You promised!
我什么也没有答应过你
I promised you nothing!
跟我走吧
Jamais!
绝不
Never!
我要去罗马了
I am leaving for Rome.
请你… 请你跟我一起走
Please, please come with me.
我已经放手了 我再没有什么可以给你的了
I have given and I have no more to give.
为什么 为什么你要这么对待我？
Why, why do you treat me like this!
不
No!
走啊 走 给我走
GO, go, go, go!
无情… 卑鄙
Heartless... fiend!
就在那一刻 爱情死去了 憎恨萌生了
It was at that moment, that love died and hate was born.
《三角墙山庄》
维奥莱特
Violet...
你好 华生 你来得正好
Ah, Watson, well timed.
跟史提夫·迪克西握个手吧 他是位拳击手
Shake hands with Steve Dixie, the pugilist,
他在这一行可是前途无量啊
who might have a future in his profession,
如果不结交损友的话
if he didn't mix with bad company.
这儿到底发生了什么事？
What on earth's been happening here?
哎 让他少管闲事
Him meddlin' in affairs what don't concern 'im.
我警告了他 可是他目中无人
Now, I warned 'im and he got cocky...
不不 说吧说吧 没事儿
No, keep talking, keep talking! It's fine. Mmm.
没关系 是吧？
It's fine, isn't it?
哼 要是我狠狠地揍你一顿 还会没事儿吗？
Well, it won't be so damn fine if I have to thump you around a bit.
别动手 华生 别动手
Stop it, Watson, Stop it!
我们听听 是谁派他来滋事生非的
Let us hear who has sent him on the belligerent errand.
坐下 迪克西
Sit down, Dixie.
跟我谈谈吧
Talk to me.
哈 谢谢 现在告诉我是怎么回事
Ah, thank you. Now tell me what this is all about.
我什么也不会说的 福尔摩斯先生 我只想告诉你离哈罗远点
I'm tellin' you nothin', Mr. Holmes. Except you keep away from Harrow.
我这几个月都没去过哈罗
I haven't been to Harrow in months.
你知道我在说什么 我警告你
You know what I'm talkin' about, I'm warnin' you!
离得远点
Keep away!
关于在霍尔伯恩酒吧外 珀金斯被杀一事…
On the matter of the killing of Perkins outside the Holborn bar...
跟我一点关系也没有
I had nothin' to do with that!
那男孩被杀的时候
I was trainin', yeah,
我正在伯明翰的斗牛场上 进行着训练
at the Bull Ring in Birmingham when that boy got done.
这个你跟治安官说去
You'll tell that to the Magistrate.
哈德森太太
Mrs. Hudson!
瞧 不要太激动嘛 对吧 福尔摩斯先生
Look, er, no hard feelin's eh, Mr. Holmes.
哈德森太太 这里有点小骚乱
Mrs. Hudson. There's been a slight disturbance.
噢
I er,
我只是听命于人
I just done what I was told.
替我问候巴尼·斯托克代尔
My regards to Barney Stockdale.
就是你把这儿搞得一团糟的吗
You are responsible for this mess.
马上给我下去 下楼去
Go on, down those stairs with you at once.
噢 他真是个温顺的家伙 胆子又小 你都看到了
Oh, he's a harmless enough fellow and easily cowed as you see.
他是斯宾塞·约翰团伙里的一个 专搞袭击恐吓之类的事情
One of the Spencer John gang. Assaults, intimidation and the like.
他们干嘛要恐吓你？
Why would they want to intimidate you?
谁是巴尼·斯托克代尔？
And who's Barney Stockdale.
他是他的上级主使
His immediate principal.
又是谁付钱给巴尼·斯托克代尔呢？
Oh, who's paying Barney Stockdale, I wonder?
哈罗·威尔德的三角墙山庄
"The Three Gables, Harrow Weald"?
他打烂了我们的窗户
He's broken our window!
亲爱的歇洛克.福尔摩斯先生
"Dear Mr. Sherlock Holmes, "
我这里发生了一连串
"I have had a succession of strange incidents occur to me"
跟我的屋子有关的怪事
"in connection with my house,"
我想听听您的意见
"and I should much value your advice."
明天随时欢迎您光临寒舍
You would find me at home any time tomorrow.
我已故的丈夫莫提默·曼伯利
"I believe that my late husband, Mortimer Maberley"
曾是您早期的主顾之一
"was one of your early clients."
您忠诚的
"Yours faithfully,"
玛丽·曼伯利
"Mary Maberley."
史提夫·迪克西带来的这个有趣插曲
This comic interlude with Steve Dixie
让我相信这里头一定有古怪
convinces me there must be something in it.
我们发电报给她 然后马上动身吧
Let us wire her and go out there at once.
您丈夫跟我相当熟悉 夫人 不过那是很多年前的事情了
I knew your husband well, madam, but it was some years ago.
嗯 我的丈夫 他去世也有些年头了
Well, it is some years since he was with us, the dear man.
要不要尝点这个？我自己烤的
Oh, will you try some of this? I baked it myself.
那位是道格拉斯·曼伯利吗
That's Douglas Maberley?
是的
Yes.
我跟他有些浅交 他很出色
I knew him slightly. Ah, he's a splendid fellow.
他在我以前的黑荒原俱乐部打橄榄球
Plays rugby for my old club, Blackheath.
我是他的奶奶
I am his grandmother.
我曾经是他的奶奶
I was his grandmother.
他一个月前去世了
He died a month ago.
去世了？
Died?
你没听说吗？是的 让人伤心的结局
You hadn't heard? No, no, It was a sad ending.
噢 真遗憾
Oh, I am so sorry...
他看上去是那么充满活力 很难把他和死亡联系在一起
He seemed so full of life and energy, It, it's hard to connect...
他的感情过于丰富了
He lived too intensely.
这一点把他毁了
It was the ruin of him.
是一起意外吧？我上次还听说
But, was it an accident? I mean, I mean the last thing I heard, he,
他被派往罗马的使馆工作呢
he'd been appointed attache to our Embassy in Rome.
他就在这房子里头死的 他们说是肺炎
He died in this house. Of pneumonia, they say.
是由脾脏破裂引起的
Brought on by a ruptured spleen.
不过我今天请你们来 不是要来谈我孙子的
But it's not to talk of my grandson that I asked you here.
我们都来了
Well, we are here, please.
是来为您效劳的
To give you service.
谢谢
Thank you. Well,
我在这房子里住了有一年多 过着隐居的生活
I have been in this house for over a year now, leading a retired life.
三天前我接到一个房产经纪的电话
Three days ago, I had a call from a house agent.
钱不是问题 夫人
The money is no object, madam.
可是附近有好几间待售的屋子呢
But there's several empty houses round here on the market.
不 就要这间 我的委托人对这间屋子情有独钟
No, This. My client's heart is set on this one.
你开个价好吗？
Will you name your price?
我开的价比买进价高了500英镑
I suggested five hundred pounds more than I gave for it,
他说他的委托人…
but he said that his client...
我的委托人还想连家具一起买
My client desires to buy the furniture as well.
全部家具吗？
All of it?
是的
Everything.
有些家具可是上等质地的啊
But some of it's very good.
尽管开价就行 曼伯利太太
Just state your price Mrs. Maberley.
于是我就开了个高价 他马上就答应了
So I did. A good round sum and he agreed at once.
我一直希望有可能的话能去周游世界
You see, I always wanted to travel, around the World if I could.
这也是我先生的遗愿
It's a legacy left to me by my dear Mortimer,
我们从未实现过
though alas we never really achieved it.
那人第二天回来时 是不是把协议都起草好了？
The man returned the next day with everything drawn up?
就是昨天的事 幸好我把协议 给我的律师苏特罗先生看了
Yesterday. Luckily, I showed it to Mr. Sutro, my lawyer.
真是怪事
This is very strange.
你有没有注意到 协议不许你带走房子里的任何东西
Are you aware that you cannot take anything out of the house.
甚至是你个人的财产也不行？
Not even your own personal possessions?
我的衣服也不行吗？还有我的珠宝？
Not my clothes? My jewellery?
什么都不行
Anything-
那个人再来的时候 您有没有向他指出这一点？
When the men returned to the house, you pointed this out.
有的
Yes.
他说我可以带走一些个人的东西
He said I might take some personal effects.
但是要带走的东西 一律得经过检查
But that nothing should go out of this house unchecked.
我的委托人很慷慨
My client is very liberal.
但有些怪癖 夫人 做事情有他自己的方式
But has fads, Madam, and a way of doing things.
你的东西嘛 我的委托人要么就全要
I'm afraid it must be everything,
要么就全部都不要
or nothing for my client.
那就全都不要好了
Then it must be nothing.
这就是他的名片
Here it is.
海恩斯·约翰逊 拍卖估价师 没有留下地址
"Haines Johnson, Auctioneer Valuer. No address."
我怀疑我们能否在号码本里找到他
I should doubt we shall find him in the directory.
诚实的人不会隐瞒自己的地址的
Honest men don't conceal their place of business.
对于偷听的来说 你的喘息声太大了
Just a little wheezy for eavesdropping.
我只不过想进来问问 客人们是否会
I, I just came in to find out if the visitors was
留下来用午餐 夫人
stayin' for lunch, Madam.
别逼我用这个
Don't force me to use this.
曼伯利太太
Mrs. Maberley,
您有没有跟别人说起过要向我咨询的事？
did you mention to anyone that you were going to consult me?
没有 福尔摩斯先生
I did not, Mr. Holmes.
信是谁寄的？
Who posted the letter?
苏珊
Susan did.
苏珊？哈 你把消息透露给谁了？
Susan, aah. To whom did you send your message?
我没有向别人透露什么消息
I sent no message.
告诉我
Tell me.
苏珊 我记起来了
Susan! I remember now.
我看见你在篱笆那里跟人说话来着
I saw you speaking to someone over the hedge.
那是我的私事 夫人
That was my own business, Madam.
是巴尼·斯托克代尔
Barney Stockdale.
怎么可能 我都不认识他
Fine chance that'd be. I don't even know the man.
要是你告诉我 这事是谁在背后搞的鬼 我给你10英镑
It is worth ten pounds to you if you tell me who is at the back of this.
你的10英镑的消息
Someone who could lay down a thousand pounds
有人可愿意花上1000镑呢
for every ten you've got in the world.
我看见一个有钱人在微笑 是一个有钱的女人
Is he a rich man? You smiled, a rich woman.
把名字告诉我 你就可以把钱拿去
Tell the name, and earn the money.
我要先看到你下地狱
I'll see you in hell first.
明天我派人来取我的箱子 夫人
I'll send for my box tomorrow... Madam.
这群团伙出现意味着有猫腻
This gang means business.
可是他们想要什么呢？
But what can they possibly want?
曼伯利太太 您说您在这房子里住了有一年了？
Mrs. Maberley. You say you've been in this house for a year.
差不多两年
Nearly two.
这么说 近两年来
So, for nearly two years,
没人对这房子 有什么特别的兴趣
no one has taken any particular interest in the house,
然而就在三四天前 突然就有人这么急需
and yet, suddenly within three or four days,
这房子和里头的东西
urgent demands are made for it, and its contents.
房子里肯定添置了什么新的东西
Something new must have been brought into the house.
没有 我有一年多没买什么新东西了
No, I haven't bought anything new for a year.
这个苏珊来这儿多久了？
This Susan. How long has she been with you?
大概三个星期
Almost three weeks.
就在你孙子死后吗？
Since your grandson's death?
他去世一星期后的事
Oh, a week after.
她向我自荐
She presented herself.
而我就雇佣了她 呃 也没有什么介绍信
I mean, I took her in, I suppose, without proper reference.
这蛋糕很好吃
Do you know, this cake is delicious.
能说说 您孙子
Please, now will you tell us about the circumstances of your-
从意大利回来的情形吗？
Grandson's return from Italy.
我那多情的孩子
My gallant boy...
你也许还记得 他曾是一个 多么快活 优秀的人吧 华生医生
you may remember him as debonair and splendid, Dr. Watson.
你都没有看到 他变得多么郁郁寡欢心事重重
You didn't see the morose and brooding creature he became.
他的心都碎了
His heart is broken.
一月之间 我看着他变成了一个衰弱又愤世嫉俗的人
In a single month, I Watched him turn into a worn-out cynical man.
女人吗？
A woman?
他不肯说
He wouldn't speak of it...
他说他怕让他的奶奶也跟着烦恼
He was afraid of upsetting his grand mama, he said.
那您一直都不知道她的名字了？
And so you never learnt her name?
今晚最好能有人 跟您呆在一起 华生？
It might be advisable for someone to stay with you tonight. Watson?
好的 没问题
Yes, of course.
不 我真的不能麻烦你
Oh, no. I really couldn't ask such a thing.
不不不 我们要走了
No, no, no, no. Willingly.
谢谢 曼伯利太太
Thank you Mrs. Maberley.
我天黑前回来 您别担心
I shall be back before dark. Don't concern yourself.
也许要找到这个人才行 她叫什么？维奥莱特吗？
It might be useful to find this erm, what's she called, Violet?
他也许向她透露了什么事情 他到死也没有
He may have confided something to her that he didn't tell his grandmother,
跟他奶奶说起的事情
in his last hours?
福尔摩斯？
Holmes?
下午好 迪克西先生
Good afternoon, Mr. Dixie.
那老太太和她的房子 都在我的保护之下
The old lady and the house are both under my protection.
你可别忘了
And don't you forget it.
看看他们是不是走了 今晚带上你的手枪
Make sure they're gone. Bring your revolver tonight.
D代表道格拉斯·曼伯利
"D", Douglas Maberley.
出色 快活 同时又阴郁 愤世嫉俗 好重的词
Splendid, debonair, to morose cynical... Strong words.
噢 不
Oh, no. No. Oh!
这个没有眼睛的女士是谁？
Who is this lady with no eyes.
我们去那边查
Our course lies there.
应该是样连她自己都不知道 已经在手上的东西
It must be something she doesn't know she has.
就算她知道 也许也不肯告诉我们
And probably wouldn't tell us, even if she did know.
这案子要找兰代尔·派克
This is a case for Langdale Pike.
那个卑鄙的无赖
That reptile?
胡说 他是个爱讲闲话的人
Nonsense. Don't talk rubbish. He's a gossip, of course.
也许他能指认出那个贵妇人
He might identify this rich woman.
真是令人难过 他在大学的时候可是很出色的
Sad, he was brilliant at university.
我总觉得 在他外表之下
And yet, I've always felt that underneath that veneer,
藏着一颗孤独的心 就像我
that he was totally isolated, like me.
你看到了吗？那边在树下的女孩
You see that, that young girl there, under the tree,
戴着一顶应景的帽子 你觉得她在干嘛？
with the occasional hat. What do you make of her?
她在找她的狗
She is looking for her dog.
什么？不 当然不是
What? No, no... surely...
一条萨卢基狗 也许戴着松绿色的项圈
A Salukee with a turquoise collar perhaps.
她对这公园很陌生 她的狗也是
She is a stranger in the park. So is the dog.
它来了
There it is now.
你怎么知道的？
How did you know that?
她的靴子是乡村款式的
Her boots are country boots
但已经不够结实 说明她来自崎岖的丘陵地区
but not so robust as to suggest a rough terrain.
威尔特郡来的 也许是来自格洛斯特郡
Wiltshire, Gloucestershire perhaps.
是的 是的 但是…
Yes, yes, yes, but...
你有没有发现她很迷人？
Don't you find her attractive?
好吧 为什么是一条萨卢基狗？
Alright. Why a Salukee?
人们常说"狗似主人形"
Owners are meant to look like their dogs, they say.
难道不就是萨卢基了吗？
Wouldn't you say Salukee?
厉害
Remarkable.
事实上 她是杰拉尔丁·温德里奇小姐
She is, in point of fact, Lady Geraldine Windridge...
来自威尔特郡的莫尔伯勒家的近亲
The Close, Marlborough, Wiltshire.
现在说说 亲爱的福尔摩斯 你找我干嘛来了？
And now, my dear Holmes, what is it you really want from me?
是关于已故的道格拉斯 曼伯利
The late Douglas Maberley...
可怜的孩子 真是可惜了
Poor boy. And what a waste.
他与一位女士有染 一位贵妇人
He was involved with a lady. A well-placed rich lady.
你知道吗？
Known to you?
你有什么可以交换的吗
Have you something to trade?
有来有往？
Tittle for tattle?
兰代尔 我很急的
Langdale... I'm in a hurry.
嗯 谢谢
Thank you.
她名叫伊莎多拉·克莱恩
Her name is Isadora Klein.
啊 没错 是德国糖业大王的遗孀 相当出名的一位美人儿
Ah, yes. Widow of the German sugar king. Quite a celebrated beauty.
著名的美人儿
The celebrated beauty.
她和年轻的洛蒙德公爵订了婚 就要结婚了
She's engaged to be married to the youthful Duke of Lomond.
派克还告诉你什么了？有没有告诉你她和曼伯利的事？
What else did Pike tell you? Anything about her and Maberley?
没有
Nothing.
福尔摩斯
I wonder, Holmes.
你觉得有没有可能
Do you think it could be about some-
她想拿回一些有损声名的信件？
compromising letters she wants retrieving?
特别是会影响她即将举行的婚礼的信件
I mean, particularly in view of her forthcoming marriage?
你是说情信吗？不 不 应该不止这样
You mean love letters? No, no, it's deeper than that.
听着 我要你
Listen, I demand that you spend
在三角墙山庄 彻夜守候
a sleepless night at The Three Gables.
枪不离手
With that revolver at hand.
你今晚怎么过？
And how will you be spending the evening?
从另一个角度追踪这个案件 去查一下当事人
Pursuing the matter from another angle. Examining the principle.
你有什么要告诉我的 米格尔？
So, what is it you have to tell me, Miguel?
那个愚蠢的苏珊已经 离开曼伯利家的房子了
That stupid woman, Susan, has left the Maberley house.
他无视我们要他远离哈罗的要求
He has refused our request to avoid Harrow.
歇洛克.福尔摩斯
Sherlock Holmes.
那是因为你的要求不够强硬
Then you did not "request" him hard enough.
那么
Well,
歇洛克.福尔摩斯先生在调查这个案子了
so Mr. Sherlock Holmes is on the case.
他拜访了那位老妇人
He paid a visit to the old lady,
不过空手而返
but left empty handed, have no fear.
今晚就得动手
we must act tonight,
你安排一下
arrange it.
这位福尔摩斯先生倒是引起了我的兴趣
This Mr. Sherlock Holmes intrigues me.
他聪明吗？
Is he clever?
他可是声名在外
He has a reputation.
侦破疑案很出名 没错
For solving crimes, yes.
可是对付女人呢？
But for women?
你还欠我一个人情 伙计 你记得吗？
You still owe me a favour dear boy. Remember?
你要是不还我人情 那张纸我可不撕掉
I shan't destroy the paper until you've returned the compliment.
还记得吧 有来有往？
Remember. Tittle for Tattle.
看看你 到底怎么啦？
Look at you. I mean what sort of...
啊 当然了 我们现在参加的是中产阶级的化妆晚会
Oh, of course, we are above the bourgeois epatant of costume.
狂欢已经开始了
The revels have begun.
就算没有你那朦胧的谜题 生活也已经够神秘了
Life is mystery enough without your pale conundrums?
噢 这么多人 却如此没有目标
Oh, so many people, so little purpose.
那是上帝的谜题
That's God's conundrum.
要是我们这样的凡夫俗子能回答就好了
If only we mortals could answer that...
那你的生活也没什么意思了
Then your life would have no meaning.
啊 残酷
Ahh cruel,
真实却又残酷 残酷但很真实
cruel, cruel, but so true.
我总是说我们已故的朋友
I have always said that if our late mutual friend,
查尔斯·米尔沃顿是个坏天使
Charles Augustus Milverton was the bad angel,
而我可是个好天使 我秘而不宣的事比我透露的可是多得多
I am the good angel. I suppress much, much more than I expose.
否则 这世界会怎样呢？
What sort of world would it be, if I didn't?
她是哪一位？
Which one is she?
在那边 亲爱的
Over there, my dear fellow.
你不会认错她的 跟年轻的洛蒙德在一起
You could hardly mistake her, with young Lomond.
《无情的美妇人》(济慈的一首诗)
La belle dame sans merci.
道格拉斯 曼伯利
Douglas Maberley.
还有其他人 其他 其他 还有其他
And others. All those, all those, all those.
道格拉斯是伦敦 最为引人注目的年轻人之一
Douglas, was one of the most striking young men in London...
他倾尽所有 也希望得到一切
He gave all and expected all.
唉
Alas!
是她结束了这段关系
It was she who ended it.
残忍地 嫁给一位出身平凡 不名一文的外交官
Brutally. Marriage with a penniless diplomat of little breeding
可不在这寡妇的计划之中
was not in the widow's plans.
你没读过我的专栏吗？
Don't you read my column?
然而他好像 死后还握着她的什么把柄
And yet he seems, even in death, to have some hold over her.
是什么呢？
What is it?
我给你提供的资料 你想怎么用都行
Do what you like with the information I gave you,
不过不要跟她做交易
but have no truck with her. She...
瞧 看见她都让我毛发直竖
Look, the sight of her set my hairs on end.
她是致命的
She is deadly.
而现在 伟大的公爵都被她操控于股掌之中
And now she has a great ducal line within her grasp.
看看他们 她都老得可以当他的…
And look at them. She is old enough to be his...
啊 那苦恼的母亲
Ah, the anguished mother.
我曾经帮过她丈夫
I helped her husband once.
你现在找她干嘛呢？
What is your interest in her now?
道格拉斯已经作古了 他已经归于尘土了
Douglas is history, he's dust, dust!
我们不都这样吗？不都这样吗？
Aren't we all, aren't we all.
连你也一样
Even you.
我可不是 伙计 我可不是
Not me, dear boy. Not me!
我可是能经受住时间的风霜的
I withstand the blasts of time!
你没发现吗？
Can't you see?
晚上好
Good evening.
当时我正要动身去印度 当一户人家的家庭女教师
I was on my way to India, Governess to a family,
刚好就碰到了我亲爱的莫提默 他走的是另一条路线
when I met my dear Mortimer. He was going the other way.
这是他当时戴的帽子 60多年前了
Aah, this is the hat he was wearing, over sixty years ago.
可您从没到过印度吧？
But you, you never got to India?
是的 我回头跟他一起走了
No. I turned back and went with him.
噢 当时好多人反对
Oh, the fuss!
那时他是个身无分文的推销员
You see, he was a penniless salesman at the time.
卖整肠药水的 就是治婴儿肚痛的
Erm, Gripe water, you know, things for babies' tummies.
可是他骨子里是个爱冒险的人
But in his heart and soul there was adventure.
我们计划去周游全世界
Ah, the places we planned to visit, all over the world...
可是我们从没有离开过哈罗
We never left Harrow.
这照片上是莫提默和道格拉斯吗？
Is er, is this Mortimer, wi, wi... with Douglas?
噢 天哪 我竟还保存着它 真是太好了
Oh, good Heavens, have I kept that? How wonderful.
他们彼此深爱对方
Oh. They doted on each other.
他俩在很多方面都很相似 一个模子印出来的
They were alike in so many ways. Two peas in a pod.
他的父母亲怎么了？
Er, what, happened to his, his mother and father?
我儿子和儿媳 在攀登斯诺登尼亚峰的时候死于了意外
Oh, my son and his wife were killed in a climbing accident in Snowdonia,
那时道格拉斯只有两岁
when Douglas was only two years old.
我们养大了他 把他当作自己的孩子
We brought him up as our own, you see.
哈罗的案子？
This case in Harrow?
跟你未来的儿媳
It concerns your future daughter-in-law,
跟她的一位已故的熟人有关 事实对她不利
and a late acquaintance of hers. The facts do her no credit.
她过去的风流韵事？
Something from her past.
我就知道 请马上告诉我
I knew it. Tell me at once.
我还需要点时间
I need a little time.
令我难过的婚礼很快就到了
The wedding which I deplore, is almost upon us.
我那好孩子
My golden boy.
他被这女人迷得神魂颠倒
He is besotted with this woman.
要是你知道什么对她不利的事情
If you know something against her,
求你现在就揭晓吧
pray God let the scandal break, now.
噢 不不不 我想丑闻是可以避免的
Oh, no, no, no. I think a scandal can be avoided.
有什么我能做的吗？
Is there anything you wish me to do?
我需要的就是这次会面罢了
Granting me this interview was all that I needed.
克莱恩夫人在这儿见到我 可是不会高兴的
Mrs. Klein will not have been pleased to see me here.
克莱恩夫人
Mrs. Klein.
哈瑞在坟墓里都会不得安宁的
Harry would be turning in his grave.
都交给我来办吧
Leave all to me, please.
曼伯利太太
Mrs. Maberley?
快去
Oh, leave me.
去追他们 他们得手了 走啊
Go after them! They've got it! Go!
噢 请快点 哦
Please, hurry. Oh.
噢 快啊
Oh. Oh, hurry. Please. Oh!
史提夫·迪克西
Steve Dixie.
福尔摩斯先生 福尔摩斯先生 醒醒
Mr. Holmes, Mr. Holmes wake up!
大事不好了
It's bad news, I'm afraid.
醒醒 福尔摩斯先生
Wake-up, Mr. Holmes.
福尔摩斯先生？
Mr. Holmes.
不好了 福尔摩斯先生 医生他…
It, it's bad news, Mr. Holmes. It's the doctor.
他在哈罗受到了严重的袭击
He, he's been brutally attacked in Harrow.
不 不 他还活着
Oh, no, no, he is alive.
他… 或是律师发电报过来了
He wired, or, or rather the lawyer did, to say
说要是你不在的话 让我务必找到你
I was to find you if you weren't in,
还要你尽快赶到那儿去
and you're to get there as soon as possible.
我会给他做好吃的鲭鱼 给他当茶点
And I'd got him a nice piece of mackerel for his tea.
多拉 华生医生在哪儿？
Dora. Where is Dr. Watson?
他在楼上 先生
He's upstairs, sir.
他怎么样了？
How is he?
我不知道 先生 他早餐吃得不错
I don't know, sir. He had a good breakfast.
你家女主人呢？
Your mistress?
她在休息 先生
She's restin', sir.
她伤得不重 可是很受惊
She weren't badly hurt, but she's had a nasty shock,
我们都是
we all have.
老天啊 你都碰上什么事了？
Good Lord, what have you run into?
发生了什么事？
What happened?
太太说你一到她就要见你
Madam says she wants to see you,
福尔摩斯先生
as soon as you arrive Mr. Holmes, sir.
福尔摩斯 她现在很虚弱
Holmes, she is in a very frail condition.
医生 先医好你自己再说吧
Physician, heal thyself.
福尔摩斯先生 你可真好
Mr. Holmes... how good of you.
您觉得怎么样？
How are you feeling?
呃 我还活着 多亏了您勇敢的朋友 华生医生
I'm alive. Thanks to your brave friend, Doctor Watson.
他把它从他们手里夺回来了吗？
Did he get it back from them?
夺回什么？
Get what?
噢 对了 你还不知道 我没有…
Oh, of course, you wouldn't know, I don't...
福尔摩斯先生 我得向您道歉
Mr. Holmes. I owe you an apology.
我原先希望它跟这件事无关 可它真的有关
I, I prayed it would have no bearing, but it it does...
我真是太蠢了
Oh, so stupid of me...
它就是一切的根源
It's the reason for everything.
道格拉斯在写书
Douglas was writing a book.
他说书里会解释一切 他在罗马的时候开始提笔
He said it would explain it all. He started it in Rome.
后来他们把他送回这里后
And later, when they brought him back here,
他就在那个通风的避暑亭里 坐上几个小时写东西
he, he sat for hours in that draughty little summer house,
甚至在十分糟糕的天气里
writing... sometimes in the most dreadful weather.
后来他连床都起不来了
And later, when he could no longer leave his room,
可他还是挣扎着写他的书
he still struggled with it.
有两本
Two copies.
一本他给了维奥莱特
One he gave to Violet...
要她把书寄给某个人 我不知道是谁
and told her to deliver it to someone, I, I, don't know who.
他要她发誓保密的 而她也信守诺言
He had sworn her to secrecy and she kept her promise.
另外一本
The other copy...
他催促我 几乎用尽他的最后一口气
He urged me with almost with his dying breath,
要我把它拿给他的出版商
to send to his publisher.
我本来是要这么做的
I should have done so, but...
不过就在他下葬的那一夜
On the night of his funeral,
我太想念他了 于是就把整本书都看了
and missing him so much, I, I read it through.
我马上就知道那本书是什么了 那是他的一生
I knew at once what it was... His life...
还有那个女人 我甚至连她的名字都不知道
That woman... I didn't even know her name.
想到这本书会引发的丑闻
The scandal it would cause! And I,
我就把它埋在了心底 锁了起来
I shut it out of my mind, locked it away until last night
昨天晚上是华生医生让我想起了它
when Dr. Watson reminded me...
当时他们在等你吗？
And they were waiting for you.
是的 他们把它从我手里抢走
Yes, and they snatched it from me,
当时我想把它拿上去给医生看的
as I was taking it up to him...
只有这张没有拿走
All but this.
我从那个畜生手上撕下来的
I tore it from the brute.
它在哪？它在哪？米格尔
Where is it? Where is it? Miguel!
米格尔
Miguel!
最后一页 最后一页在哪儿？
The page? Where is the last page?
他拿了 我知道 是他拿了
He has it. Oh, I know he has it!
一页纸 卡丽娜 就算是福尔摩斯也不能…
One page, Carina. Not even Sherlock Holmes could...
把它烧了 别说了 把它烧了
Burn it! Don't talk! Burn it!
脸上淌着血 那些无情的殴打
"Face bled and his stomach
让他的腹中好像被火烧着一般
burned from the savage blows. "
可这些比起他滴血的心来说
"But it was nothing"
根本算不得什么
"to the bleeding of his heart."
当他看见她那可爱的脸庞
"When he saw that lovely face, "
一张他愿意为之牺牲一切的脸庞
"the face for which he had been prepared to sacrifice his life for... "
她在笑 是的 苍天可鉴 她在微笑
"She smiled, yes, by Heaven. She smiled,"
就像是个无情的魔鬼
"like the heartless fiend she was."
就在那一刻 爱情死去了
"It was at that moment that love died, "
憎恨却萌生了
"and hate was born. "
如果不是为了你的怀抱
"If it is not for your embrace, my lady,"
那就是为你的毁灭 我的夫人 为了我彻底的复仇
"then it shall be for your undoing and my complete revenge."
我彻底的复仇
"My... complete revenge."
书里的"他"变成了"我"
The "he" becomes "my".
作者把自己想象为男主人公
Yes. The writer imagines himself the hero.
有两本 一本给了克莱恩夫人
Two copies. One to Mrs. Klein.
而这本则要出版
And this for publication.
整个伦敦都会认出
All of London would recognise
人物的原型
the wolf and the lamb.
甜蜜的复仇 再把第一句读来听听
Sweet revenge. Read me the first sentence again.
脸上淌着血 那些无情的殴打 让他的腹中好像被火烧着一般
"Face bled and his stomach burned from the savage blows"
这就是死因
The cause of death!
那老太太说肺炎是脾脏破裂引起的
Pneumonia, from a ruptured spleen, the old woman said.
天哪
Good heavens.
被踢破的 那是谋杀
Ruptured from a kick. That's murder.
可是我们无法证明
We could never prove it.
我要去克里克伍德
I'm leaving for Cricklewood.
史提夫
Steve.
五个月前的格罗弗广场？
Grosvenor Square, five months ago.
那不是我 福尔摩斯先生
That weren't me, Mr. Holmes.
你不能把那栽在我头上
You can't put that on me.
是谁的靴子踢死了道格拉斯 曼伯利 也不要紧吗？
It doesn't matter whose boot killed Douglas Maberley.
你们都是有罪的
You're all guilty.
哈 苏珊
Ah, Susan!
苏珊
Susan.
在你丈夫坐牢的时候 看着你的鸡舍吧
Guarding the coup, while your husband is in prison?
新来的是谁 巴尼·斯托克代尔太太？
Watson, you remember Mrs. Barney Stockdale.
哦 是的 小心点 福尔摩斯
Oh, yes. Take care Holmes.
你们从这滚出去
You get out of 'ere.
那女人会让你坐牢的 就为你昨晚做的那事
That woman will put you behind bars for what you did last night.
而她的雇主 格罗夫纳广场的克莱恩太太
And her employer, Mrs. Klein of Grosvenor Square,
会看着你们全都因谋杀罪而被绞死
will see you all hanged for murder, unless...
除非你照我说的去做
you do what I tell you, when I tell you.
记住 霍宾的珀金斯
Remember Perkins of Holborn?
华生
Watson.
让我看看你
Let me look at you.
你看到什么了？
What do you see?
我看到了
I see...
我爱慕的女人
the woman I adore.
我准备好了 用不着 你就呆在这儿吧
I am ready now. No, stay here.
她又不是莫里亚蒂教授 她只不过是个女人
She is not Moriarty. She is a woman.
那只手需要补偿
That hand needs redressing.
记住 福尔摩斯
Just remember, Holmes.
女人可以比男人更致命
The female can be more deadly than the male.
估价师和拍卖人 哼
Valuer and Auctioneer, my foot.
啊 夫人
Ah. Madam.
又是你 福尔摩斯
You again, Holmes.
要是你有什么要对我的新娘说的
If you have something to say to my bride, speak out,
在我把你踢出去之前赶紧说吧
before I kick you out.
不 我正在等福尔摩斯先生呢 让我们单独谈谈
No. I have been expecting Mr. Holmes. Leave us.
我不打算让你跟这个…
Huh. I have no intention of leaving you with this...
去吧 詹姆斯
Go, James.
走啊
Go!
我很意外 你竟拖了这么久才来
I am only surprised it took you so long.
我意外的是 你竟然以为子弹就可以恐吓我
I am surprised that you thought bullies could frighten me.
要是危险对我没有吸引力的话
No man would take up my profession,
我也不会干这一行
it danger did not attract him.
您是一位绅士 我会把您当朋友的
You are a gentleman. I will treat you as my friend.
我可无法保证会对此作出回报
I cannot promise to reciprocate.
毫无疑问 威胁您这么勇敢的一个人是很蠢的
No doubt it was foolish to threaten such a brave man as yourself.
不 蠢的是 像您这么一位聪明的女士
No, what was really foolish of an intelligent woman like you,
竟然会让自己跟一群流氓掺和在一起
is to place yourself in the power of a-
他们可是擅于勒索 也许还会出卖您
band of rascals who could blackmail or give you away.
不不 我可不是这么头脑简单的人
Hmm. No, no. I am not so simple.
他们当中 没人知道是谁雇佣了他们
None of them have the least idea who their employer is.
巴尼·斯托克代尔和他的妻子也不知道？
Not Barney Stockdale and his wife?
他们都是很好的猎犬 能够保守秘密
They are good hounds who run silent.
还愿意为你去坐牢吗？
And are prepared to go to prison for you.
他们安之若素 他们拿了钱就该这样做
They take what comes. That's what they are paid for.
呃…
And er,
而海恩斯·约翰逊先生 噢 当然了 这不是他的真名
Mr. Haines Johnson. Oh, that surely is not his name.
他拿了钱又该干什么事？
What is he paid for?
米格尔
Miguel?
他对我就像兄弟一样亲
He is like a brother to me.
至于其他人嘛 他们都是干活的
As for the others they work,
而在这件事中我从来没有露过面
and I do not appear in the matter.
除非我把你牵扯进去
Unless I bring you into it.
可您是位绅士 福尔摩斯先生
But you are a gentleman, Mr. Holmes.
您会尊重一位女士的隐私
You respect a woman's secret?
哼 谋杀也是隐私吗？
Huh, is murder a woman's secret?
谋杀？
Murder?
我的脸上淌着血 那些无情的殴打
"My face bled, my stomach burned"
打得他的腹中好像火烧一般
"from the savage blows,
可是比起我滴血的心 那不算什么
but it was nothing to the bleeding of my heart."
第245页
Page two four five.
还有一位目击证人 克莱恩夫人
And there's a witness, Mrs. Klein.
就是职业拳手史提夫·迪克西 他将指证你
The prize fighter, Steve Dixie, who will testify against you.
这些你都告诉我未来的婆婆了吗？
And all this... you told my future mother-in-law?
我跟她说了什么并不重要
What I told the Dowager is of no importance,
因为她无法阻止
since she cannot prevent
你跟她儿子的婚姻
your marriage to her son.
是的 她是没有办法 而你觉得你可以吗？
No, she cannot. And you believe that you can?
是的
Oh, yes.
你为什么要这样做呢？
Why should you wish to?
是因为我是个外国人吗？
Is it because I am a foreigner?
你也像那些英国佬一样 是个势利鬼吗 福尔摩斯先生？
Are you an English snob, Mr. Holmes?
我来告诉你吧
Let me tell you,
我们的人几代都是 伯南布哥的领袖
my people have been leaders in Pernambuco for generations.
夫人
Madame.
你是安达卢西亚 一位吉普赛人的私生子
You are the bastard child of a gypsy in Andalucia.
你这婊子养的
Hijo de puta!
是谁告诉你的？
Who told you?
是我交换来的
It is my trade.
你必须把手稿给我
Now you must give me the manuscript.
不 不 不
No. No, no, no!
你想得到纸袋里的灰烬吗？
You wish for ashes in a paper bag?
你对我太苛刻了
You are hard to me.
看着我的眼睛 一生的抱负就要被你毁了
Look at it with my eyes. A life's ambition about to be ruined.
那是你的原罪
The original sin was yours.
是的 我认识道格拉斯
Yes, I know, Douglas.
是的 我真的爱他
Yes, I did love him, truly.
是的 我确实爱过一阵子 以我的方式爱着他
Yes, yes. I did for a while, in my fashion.
可是他要的是婚姻 这是他唯一想要的
But he wanted marriage, nothing less would serve him
但这个并不符合我的计划
and it did not fit with my plans.
于是你就雇了些流氓殴打他
And so you hired ruffians to beat him
直到他在你的窗下奄奄一息
until he was nearly dead, under your window.
难道这能算是淑女的所为吗？
Is that the act of a lady?
没错
Yes, it is true.
巴尼跟那些男孩 赶他走的时候也许是有些粗野
Barney and the boys drove him away, perhaps a little too roughly.
可他之后干了什么？
But what did he do then?
他写了本书 对我进行恶毒地人身攻击
He wrote a book, a vicious, personal attack.
那能算是绅士的所为吗？
Was that the act of a gentleman?
你知道他的出版商并没有收到这本书？
You knew this publisher had not received it.
是的 那它就应该还在他奶奶的房子里
Yes. So it had to be in the house of his grandmother.
只要这本书存在 我就不可能安全
As long as that book existed, there was no safety for me.
我想诚心地做这件事
I wanted to do this thing honestly.
我接受了她开出的任何价格
I offered any price she cared to ask,
可她不接受
but she wouldn't take it.
难道保护自己也要受到谴责吗？
Are we to be blamed for protecting ourselves?
有一件事让我感兴趣
One thing intrigues me.
为什么像你这么一位 能把男人掌握于股掌之中的美丽女士
Why a woman as lovely as you, who wields such power over men,
也需要别人的保护呢？
needs the protection of anyone?
现实才不在乎我们
Nature doesn't give a damn for any of us.
我爱詹姆斯 我想要他
I love James, and I want him.
他代表着 我想要的一切
He represents all I have ever desired,
这是我获得某种安全感的一个机会
and my one chance of a kind of security
这种安全感 我称之为幸福
which I call happiness.
而你却要把它从我这儿夺走
And you would take it away from me?
为什么？
Why?
因为你是男人的毁灭者
Because you are a destroyer of men.
噢 是的
Oh, yes.
你毁掉了道格拉斯 曼伯利
You destroyed Douglas Maberley.
还差点毁掉了我的朋友约翰 华生
And very nearly my friend, John Watson,
用你那种为了自身的利益 而不顾一切的漠然
with a ruthless disregard for anything but your own selfish interest.
为什么在你这儿就不成功了呢？
Why have I failed with you?
我的要求只有这个
I require only this.
我要读到你跟洛蒙德公爵
That I read of the breaking of your engagement
解除婚约的消息 在星期四早上之前
to the Duke of Lomond, by Thursday morning.
要是我不答应呢？
And if I refuse?
苏格兰场 会展开对证人的全面调查
Scotland Yard. A full investigation, with witnesses.
我听你发落
I am at your mercy.
- 你这个混蛋 - 悉听尊便
- Haz de me lopeor - Do your worst.
噢 坐头等舱去环游世界
Oh, how much does it cost to go round the world
要多少钱呢？我算算
in first class style? Let me see, yes.
你写一张5000英镑的支票 给曼伯利太太
You will send a cheque for five thousand pounds to Mrs. Maberley.
这是你欠她的
You owe her a little change of that.
再见 克莱恩夫人
Goodbye, Mrs. Klein.
我毫不怀疑 有一天我会再见到
I have no doubt I shall see you again one day...
你在一个国王的怀抱里
on the arm of a king.
于是克莱恩夫人 著名的美人儿
And, therefore, The celebrated beauty, Mrs. Klein"
离开前往西班牙
"has departed for Spain."
她的家族几代都是 伯南布哥的领袖
"Her people have been leaders in Pernambuco for generations."
这是一篇有品位的报道
Well, it's a dignified report,
不知道其他人会怎么评价它
I wonder what others would have made of it.
你让她脱罪了 福尔摩斯
You let her off the hook, Holmes.
你是说她犯了重罪吗？
Compounding a felony, you mean?
谋杀
Murder.
本来就是不可能证实的
It would have been impossible to prove.
克莱恩夫人已经明白了
Mrs. Klein has learnt
一个道理 那就是…
that she can't play with edged tools forever without cutting those...
"玩火者必自焚"
aging hands of hers.
岁月不饶人
Time is not on her side.
我们走吧
Shall we?